Faculty of Education fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
- Centres and departments files, 1965 - 1973; F-233-4; 64 cm of textual records
  - Professional Development Centre files, 1966 - 1971; F-233-4-3; 11 cm of textual records; Professional Development Centre
    - Program Evaluation Committee, 1971; F-233-4-3-0-18 (Archival box - standard 233-45)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-8.
  - Educational Foundations Centre files, 1969 - 1972; F-233-4-4; 13 cm of textual records; Educational Foundations Centre
    The Educational Foundations Centre (EFC) was established in 1965 as one of the original centres of the Faculty of Education. The EFC originally contained separate departments for Behaviourial Science Foundations, Social and Philosophical Foundations, and Professional Foundations. In 1970, Communicaton Studies moved from the Centre for Communications and the Arts (which left the Faculty of Education) to the EFC, while Professional Foundations separated to become its own centre. The EFC was abolished along with the remaining centres when the faculty re-organized again in 1972. In that year, Behavioural Science Foundations and Communication Studies merged and moved to the newly established Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies, while the faculty members and curriculum of Social and Philosophical Foundations joined the new unified structure of the Faculty of Education as a whole.
    Sub-series consists of records made or received by the Educational Foundations Centre and some of its committees. Activities documented include the internal re-organization of the Centre over 1969 and 1970 (incorporation of new departments), curriculum and policy development, departmental meetings, and the activities and deliberations of the Centre's Undergraduate Studies Committee and Department of Social Relations Committee. Records include correspondence, reports, proposals, course outlines, and meeting agendas and minutes. For a list of committees whose records are included in the files and other bodies represented in the correspondence, see the "Access points" section below.
    For records relating to early Education courses (EDUC), see in this fonds series 6, "Course files" (1965-1994), particularly files 2-4.
    For other records relating to the EFC, see the its correspondence with both the President and the Vice-President, Academic in their respective fonds:
    - F-193, Office of the President fonds > Series 9-4, Educational Foundations Centre (1965-1968): President's correspondence with the centre.
    - F-200, Office of the Vice-President, Academic and Provost > Series 3-2-7, Faculty of Education Centres (1968-1971): VP Academic's correspondence with each centre and its departments.
    - Amalgamation meetings, 1969; F-233-4-4-0-1 (Archival box - standard 233-46)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-3-0-3.
    - EFC meetings - agenda, minutes, supporting papers, 1969; F-233-4-4-0-2 (Archival box - standard 233-46)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-3-0-4.
    - EFC meetings - agenda, minutes, supporting papers, vol. 1, 1970; F-233-4-4-0-3 (Archival box - standard 233-46)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-3-0-5.
    - EFC meetings - agenda, minutes, supporting papers, vol. 2, 1970; F-233-4-4-0-4 (Archival box - standard 233-46)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-3-0-6.
    - Information sheets, 1970 - 1971; F-233-4-4-0-5 (Archival box - standard 233-46)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-3-0-2.
    - EFC Undergraduate Studies committee, vol. 1, 1970 - 1971; F-233-4-4-0-6 (Archival box - standard 233-46)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-3-0-8.
    - EFC Undergraduate Studies committee, vol. 2, 1970 - 1971; F-233-4-4-0-7 (Archival box - standard 233-46)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-3-0-9.
    - EFC Undergraduate Studies committee, vol. 3, 1970 - 1971; F-233-4-4-0-8 (Archival box - standard 233-46)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-3-0-10.
    - EFC meetings - agenda and minutes, 1971; F-233-4-4-0-9 (Archival box - standard 233-46)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-3-0-7.
    - Department of Social Relations Proposal, 1971 - 1972; F-233-4-4-0-10 (Archival box - standard 233-46)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-5-0-17.
- Program area files, 1968 - 1997; F-233-5; 2.75 m of textual records 31 photographs 1 sound recording; General note: 31 photographs located in F-233-5-1-1-84; sound recording (2 audio cassettes) related to file F-233-5-1-1-81.
  In 1972, the Faculty of Education re-organized, moving from a departmental structure (based on centres and departments) to a functional one, based on program area divisions. This series represents records made or recieved by the program area offices. Note that to date (July 2008) only one program area (Professional Programs, sub-series 1) has transferred records to the Archives. Records comprise primarily correspondence and reports; see sub-series descriptions for more detail.
  Series has been arranged into sub-series based on the office of origin of the material, with each program area division assigned its own sub-series, and these in turn broken down into sub-sub-series as required. Note that as of this writing (July 2008), the faculty has five main program area divisions (Undergraduate Programs, Graduate Programs, Professional Programs, Field Programs, International Programs), but only one has tranferred records to the Archives (Professional Programs = sub-series 1). When / if material from the other areas is eventually transferred and accessioned, the Archives will create additional sub-series as needed.
  Sound recordings; Photographic materials; Textual records
  - Professional Programs files, 1968 - 1997; F-233-5-1; 2.75 m of textual records 31 photographs 1 sound recording; Physical description: includes 2 audio cassettes (located in sub-sub-series 1). General note: photographs and sound recordings are located in sub-sub-series 1.; Faculty of Education. Professional Programs
    Professional Programs was established in 1972 as one of the three functional program areas that replaced the faculty's previously independent centres and departments during the re-organization of that year. It was the successor to the Professional Foundations Centre, taking over responsibility for the teacher-certification component of the Faculty of Education at SFU, and it continues as an active division of the faculty as of this writing (July 2008).
    From the opening of the university in 1965, the Faculty of Education has offered the Professional Development Program (PDP). Students could apply for PDP admission after completing a certain number of undergraduate credits at SFU or another university and, upon completion of the program, were recommended for the provincial Teachers' Certificate (granted originally by government's Department of Education, after 1974 by the British Columbia College of Teachers). The PDP program at SFU was initially administered by the Department of Professional Foundations in the Educational Foundations Centre, later (1970) becoming its own centre (Professional Foundations Centre). In 1972 responsibility for the program was carried over to faculty's new Professional Programs division. While PDP requirements and curricula have evolved over the years, it's basic structure has consistently been a three-semester program involving two core courses (EDUC 401/402), a semester of supervised classroom experience, and a semester of supplementary course programming. The faculty uses a "differentiated" or "complementary" staffing model which teams tenure-track faculty members with seconded teachers selected from school districts throughout the province. In the early 1970s the faculty initiated a decentralization of the program, enabling students to complete some of their requirements in communities outside of the Lower Mainland. In 2006, the Professional Qualifications Program (PQP) was established, a three-semester program for those wishing to re-certify their teaching credentials.
    Records consists predominantly of correspondence, reports and course-related material. See sub-series descriptions for more detailed information. The audio cassettes are found in sub-sub-series 1 ("Director's subject files").
    Sub-series was arranged into sub-sub-series by the SFU Archives based on the contents of the material.
    Further accruals to the sub-series and each of its sub-sub-series are expected.
    For other records relating to Professional Programs and its predecessor, the Professional Development Centre, see the following series in this fonds:
    - F-233-3-7, Professional Programs Committee files (1969-1986).
    - F-233-4-3, Professional Development Centre files (1966-1971).
    - F-233-7-3, Professional Programs publications (1970-1999).
    - Director's subject files, 1968 - 1997; F-233-5-1-1; 1.24 m of textual records 31 photographs 1 sound recording; Physical description: includes 2 audio cassettes (related to file 81). General notes: There is no file 133 due to a mistake in numbering during processing. Photographs are located in file 84, sound recordings relate to file 81.
      Series consists of records made or received by the Director of the Professional Programs division of the Faculty of Education in the course of administering the program area.
      Activities documented include policy development, budget planning, and staffing, including the hiring and orientation of school and faculty associates (professionals from the BC school system seconded to assist in the delivery of the PDP program); curriculum and program planning, including First Nations education, French immersion, and decentralization of SFU's PDP program; conferences, colloquia, liaison with school districts, and administration of external PDP sites; liaison with faculty task forces and committees, other units in the faculty, other SFU departments, other universities, provincial government ministries and agencies, and educational and professional associations; and student relations, advising, and post-graduation employment.
      Records include correspondence, reports, proposals, statistics, program information, orientation packages and handbooks, lists of faculty associates, policies and procedures, event schedules, notes and working papers, and printed reference material.
      For a list of organizations included in the correspondence, see the "Access points" section below.
      Faculty of Education. Task Force on Proposed Secondary Education Emphasis; Registrar's Office; British Columbia Teachers' Federation; Certification Advisory Committee; Western Canadian Association for Student Teaching; Faculty of Education. Task Force on Bachelor of Education Degree; Trinity Western University; Provincial Intermediate Teachers' Association; Provincial Intermediate Teachers' Association; Centre for Educational Technology; Jilin University (China); British Columbia Association of Math Teachers; Knowledge Network; Alaska Highway Consortium on Teacher Education; Provincial Advisory Committee on Computers; American Educational Research Association; American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education; Sound recordings; Photographic materials; Textual records
      - PDP student evaluation forms, 1968 - 1982; F-233-5-1-1-1 (Archival box - standard 233-49)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-228.
      - Letters of welcome to PDP entrants, 1973 - 1978; F-233-5-1-1-2 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-220.
      - Faculty Associates, 1974 - 1975; F-233-5-1-1-3 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-509.
      - Faculty Associate / Coordinators list, 1974 - 1975; F-233-5-1-1-4 (Archival box - standard 233-49)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-225.
      - PDP program - general, 1974 - 1976; F-233-5-1-1-5 (Archival box - standard 233-49)
      - Academic Advice advising information, 1974 - 1985; F-233-5-1-1-6 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-364.
      - School district liaison - Prince George, 1974 - 1987; F-233-5-1-1-7 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
      - Faculty Associate orientation programs, 1975 - 1976; F-233-5-1-1-8 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-265.
      - Faculty Associate appointments, 1975 - 1979; F-233-5-1-1-9 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
      - Kelowna, 1975 - 1985; F-233-5-1-1-10 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
      - Faculty Associate network, 1976; F-233-5-1-1-11 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-131.
      - Undergraduate programs, 1976 - 1987; F-233-5-1-1-12 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
      - Administrator's Colloquium, 1977; F-233-5-1-1-13 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-525.
      - Admissions policy, 1977; F-233-5-1-1-14 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-36.
      - Faculty Associate orientation programs, 1977; F-233-5-1-1-15 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-266.
      - PDP staffing formula, 1977; F-233-5-1-1-16 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-38.
      - Special Conferences: Naramata, 1977; F-233-5-1-1-17 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-138.
      - Task Force on Proposed Secondary Education Emphasis, 1977; F-233-5-1-1-18 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-85.
      - Appeals policy, 1977 - 1978; F-233-5-1-1-19 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-251.
      - Education and training of teachers in BC (Leskiw report), 1977 - 1978; F-233-5-1-1-20 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-480.
      - Program consultants papers, 1977 - 1978; F-233-5-1-1-21 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-5-1-0-2.
      - Correspondence, 1977 - 1979; F-233-5-1-1-22 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-340.
      - Faculty Associate role, 1977 - 1979; F-233-5-1-1-23 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-276.
      - Teacher education statistics outside agencies, 1977 - 1980; F-233-5-1-1-24 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
      - Interior sites, 1977 - 1981; F-233-5-1-1-25 (Archival box - standard 233-56)
      - Registrar, 1977 - 1981; F-233-5-1-1-26 (Archival box - standard 233-57)
      - Lists of faculty members, Coordinators, Faculty Associates, 1977 - 1982; F-233-5-1-1-27 (Archival box - standard 233-49)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-243.
      - British Columbia Teachers Federation (BCTF) Teacher Education Committee, 1977 - 1984; F-233-5-1-1-28 (Archival box - standard 233-57)
      - Employment information for PDP students - booklets, reports and correspondence, 1977 - 1984; F-233-5-1-1-29 (Archival box - standard 233-57)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-356.
      - Admissions Information - Correspondence and Papers, 1977 - 1985; F-233-5-1-1-30 (Archival box - standard 233-57)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-355.
      - PDP Program Coordinator, 1977 - 1985; F-233-5-1-1-31 (Archival box - standard 233-49)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-341.
      - British Columbia Teachers Federation (BCTF), 1977 - 1987; F-233-5-1-1-32 (Archival box - standard 233-57)
      - Faculty Associate orientation programs, 1978; F-233-5-1-1-33 (Archival box - standard 233-57)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-267.
      - PDP budget, 1978; F-233-5-1-1-34 (Archival box - standard 233-57)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-219.
      - Assistant Director memoranda, 1978 - 1980; F-233-5-1-1-35 (Archival box - standard 233-57)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-257.
      - Miscellaneous papers, 1978 - 1982; F-233-5-1-1-36 (Archival box - standard 233-57)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-5-1-0-1.
      - Open Education Alternative, 1978 - 1983; F-233-5-1-1-37 (Archival box - standard 233-57)
      - Faculty Associate orientation programs, 1979; F-233-5-1-1-38 (Archival box - standard 233-57)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-268.
      - Independent schools proposal, 1979; F-233-5-1-1-39 (Archival box - standard 233-57)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-382.
      - Tri-Universities Committee: interior, 1979; F-233-5-1-1-40 (Archival box - standard 233-57)
      - Faculty Associates, 1979 - 1980; F-233-5-1-1-41 (Archival box - standard 233-57)
      - Program tasks, 1979 - 1982; F-233-5-1-1-42 (Archival box - standard 233-49)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-316.
      - School district liaison - Coquitlam, 1979 - 1983; F-233-5-1-1-43 (Archival box - standard 233-57)
      - British Columbia Teachers Federation (BCTF) - Program sponsor teacher, 1979 - 1984; F-233-5-1-1-44 (Archival box - standard 233-57)
      - Faculty Associate lists, 1979 - 1984; F-233-5-1-1-45 (Archival box - standard 233-58)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-370.
      - Summary of research and evaluation activities, 1979 - 1984; F-233-5-1-1-46 (Archival box - standard 233-58)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-371.
      - Abstracts of PDP reports, 1980; F-233-5-1-1-47 (Archival box - standard 233-58)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-334.
      - External agencies overview, 1980; F-233-5-1-1-48 (Archival box - standard 233-58)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-463.
      - Outline of a staff training model, 1980; F-233-5-1-1-49 (Archival box - standard 233-58)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-89.
      - School Associate Tuition Fee Certificate, 1980; F-233-5-1-1-50 (Archival box - standard 233-58)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-229.
      - Education Advising Handbook, 1980 - 1981; F-233-5-1-1-51 (Archival box - standard 233-58)
      - Faculty Associate orientation program objectives, 1980 - 1981; F-233-5-1-1-52 (Archival box - standard 233-58)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-269.
      - Statistics - employment of PDP graduates, 1980 - 1981; F-233-5-1-1-53 (Archival box - standard 233-58)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-256.
      - Learning Resources Centre, 1980 - 1982; F-233-5-1-1-54 (Archival box - standard 233-58)
      - PDP interior programming, 1980 - 1983; F-233-5-1-1-55 (Archival box - standard 233-49)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-315.
      - Program articulation -Douglas College, 1980 - 1983; F-233-5-1-1-56 (Archival box - standard 233-58)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-450.
      - April Program tasks/components, 1980 - 1984; F-233-5-1-1-57 (Archival box - standard 233-58)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-317.
      - School district liaison - Vancouver, 1980 - 1985; F-233-5-1-1-58 (Archival box - standard 233-58)
      - Multiculturalism, 1980 - 1986; F-233-5-1-1-59 (Archival box - standard 233-58)
      - Certification Advisory Committee (CAC), vol. 1, 1980 - 1987; F-233-5-1-1-60 (Archival box - standard 233-49)
      - Certification Advisory Committee (CAC), vol. 2, 1980 - 1987; F-233-5-1-1-61 (Archival box - standard 233-49)
      - Certification Advisory Committee (CAC), vol. 3, 1980 - 1987; F-233-5-1-1-62 (Archival box - standard 233-49)
      - Administrative and organizational planning, 1981; F-233-5-1-1-63 (Archival box - standard 233-58)
      - Correspondence, 1981; F-233-5-1-1-64 (Archival box - standard 233-58)
      - PDP Coordinator evaluation, 1981; F-233-5-1-1-65 (Archival box - standard 233-58)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-342.
      - Early Childhood Education (Burnaby Liaison), 1981 - 1982; F-233-5-1-1-66 (Archival box - standard 233-58)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-349.
      - Faculty Associates, 1981 - 1982; F-233-5-1-1-67 (Archival box - standard 233-58)
      - Interior program proposals, 1981 - 1982; F-233-5-1-1-68 (Archival box - standard 233-58)
      - Internship planning, 1981 - 1982; F-233-5-1-1-69 (Archival box - standard 233-58)
      - Professional Programs Committee and Bachelor of Education Task Force, 1981 - 1982; F-233-5-1-1-70 (Archival box - standard 233-59)
      - Art Education Program proposal, 1981 - 1983; F-233-5-1-1-71 (Archival box - standard 233-59)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-359.
      - Kindergarten proposal, 1981 - 1984; F-233-5-1-1-72 (Archival box - standard 233-59)
      - British Columbia Teachers Federation (BCTF) - Project TEACH, 1981 - 1985; F-233-5-1-1-73 (Archival box - standard 233-59)
      - PDP advertising information, 1981 - 1985; F-233-5-1-1-74 (Archival box - standard 233-59)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-362.
      - PDP French programming, 1981 - 1986; F-233-5-1-1-75 (Archival box - standard 233-59)
      - PDP programs - general, vol. 1, 1981 - 1986; F-233-5-1-1-76 (Archival box - standard 233-59)
      - PDP programs - general, vol. 2, 1981 - 1986; F-233-5-1-1-77 (Archival box - standard 233-59)
      - Western Canadian Association for Student Teaching (WESTCAST), 1981 - 1986; F-233-5-1-1-78 (Archival box - standard 233-59)
      - Graduates, 1981 - 1987; F-233-5-1-1-79 (Archival box - standard 233-59)
      - Social functions, 1981 - 1988; F-233-5-1-1-80 (Archival box - standard 233-59)
      - PDP on Trial symposium, vol. 1, 1982; F-233-5-1-1-81 (Archival box - standard 233-59)
        - PDP on Trial symposium, 1982; F-233-5-1-1-81-1 (Audio cassette OBJ-3940, Audio cassette OBJ-3941)
          Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-233-item5.
      - PDP on Trial symposium, vol. 2, 1982; F-233-5-1-1-82 (Archival box - standard 233-60)
      - PDP on Trial symposium, vol. 3, 1982; F-233-5-1-1-83 (Archival box - standard 233-60)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-68.
      - PDP on Trial symposium - photos, vol. 4, 1982; F-233-5-1-1-84 (Archival box - standard 233-55)
        Photographic materials
      - School district liaison symposium, 1982; F-233-5-1-1-85 (Archival box - standard 233-60)
      - Science for elementary school teachers, 1982; F-233-5-1-1-86 (Archival box - standard 233-60)
        Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-350.
      - Faculty Associates, 1982 - 1983; F-233-5-1-1-87 (Archival box - standard 233-60)